<entry>
	<title>Open Redstone Engineers redstone server</title>
	<slug>openredstone</slug>
	<sort>5</sort>
	<type>post</type>
	<content><![CDATA[
Some time ago, I and a few internet friends started a redstone server and network called “Open Redstone Engineers”, or ORE for short, revolving around the redstone aspect in Minecraft. I wrote a bit of it in my [“about me” page](?page_id=26):

> For you who don’t know, Minecraft’s redstone is kind of like a computer electronics environment – you build gates like XOR gates, AND gates, IMPLIES gates, etc. All the gates you may know from computer science. Out of those gates, we build all kinds of crazy stuff like adders, CPUs, computers, etc. Sounds really nerdy, and I guess it is. It’s fun though.
> 
> I and a few internet friends started ORE some time back, and I’m the host for two of the redstone servers. We got:
> 
> *   main server: mc.openredstone.org
> *   school server: sc.openredstone.org
> *   survival server: ss.openredstone.org
> *   website: [openredstone.org](http://openredstone.org)
> *   YouTube channel: [youtube.com/user/openredstone](http://youtube.com/user/openredstone)
> 
> Have a look – there’s no whitelist ;) You can’t build unless you’re member though, which you get by applying.

In this post, I’d like to elaborate a bit.

Before ORE, I were a member of a similar group, called Redstone Development Foundation, or RDF. Just like ORE, it revolved around Minecraft’s redstone. I climbed in the ranks, and after a while, I became an administrator. Some time later however, stuff started falling apart, mostly due to how the administration was set up. You see, we had one person, the server host, who were responsible for everything. Updating to new versions of Minecraft, install and configure plugins, everything. The rest of the admin staff were merely moderators. We could ban and kick people, and that was pretty much it.

That system worked decently well for a while, but when the server admin became less interested in the server and generally became inactive, things didn’t go very well. We had disastrous problems stick with us for weeks at a time. One time for instance, the chat decided to act up. Once someone had written 11 messages in chat, they were kicked for spam. For about a week, we had no idea what was causing it. Another admin, redstonewarrior, decided to figure out what was wrong. Once he had figured that out, yet another week passed before the server host could be contacted and the issue got fixed.

As a result of this kind of issues, I and a few others decided to branch off and start our own redstone server and community. We got together, set up servers, wrote plugins and websites and set up a forum. We got Open Redstone Engineers rolling. Three of us were previous RDF administrators. The rest were members.

In a lot of ways, you could say we are quite similar to RDF. There are however some key differences, the biggest of which is this: _all admins got remote access to the servers_. Instead of being ruled by an almighty server host, any administrator can fix server issues.

As of writing this, the build redstone server alone gets about 300 visits per day. So yeah, we’re rolling along fairly nicely.
	]]></content>
</entry>
