<entry>
	<title>Transgenderism, an injustice at every turn</title>
	<slug>transgenderism</slug>
	<sort>14</sort>
	<type>post</type>
	<content><![CDATA[
This is a kind of topic I don't usually cover in this blog. I wrote this essay as an assignment at school where we were supposed to write about a topic related to multiculturalism. It's an extremely important topic though, which gets far less attention than it deserves. That's why I'm posting it here.

Keep in mind that I don't have extensible knowledge on the subject. I've read about it a bit and made up thoughts myself, so I may very well be wrong somewhere. Feel free to tell me tell me I'm wrong in the comments, and I'll do my best to correct it.

Transgenderism is a sort of unusual topic. The reason I bring it up is that I genuinely think it’s an extremely important topic which isn’t getting nearly enough attention.

Everywhere we go, we’re met with a strong separation between the sexes, between men and women. There’s one male section and one female section in many clothing stores — or they are either targeted at males or at females. In a lot of forms, there’s one checkbox for male, one for female. In early childhood, boys are dressed up in blue, girls in pink. Girls receive barbie dolls as toys, boys receive toy cars. Even our language reflects this strict separation; neither english nor norwegian allow for people to be anything else than masculine or feminine. Sure, we have gender neutral nouns, but those are meant for inanimate objects, not people.

**Before I proceed, I want to take a moment and look at how issues regarding transgenderism is relevant to multiculturalism.**

When we think of culture, we often think of race or ethnicity. But so it isn’t. [thefreedictionary.com has this to say about culture](http://www.thefreedictionary.com/culture):

> The totality of socially transmitted behavior patterns, arts, beliefs, institutions, and all other products of human work and thought.

Transgenderism is indeed a cultural issue. There is gay culture, and in the same way, there is transgender culture. Part of being multiculturalist is to be accepting towards all cultures, including transgender people.

That out of the way, what happens when you don’t fit into these two gender boxes our society puts us in? What happens if you’re either in between or jump the gap?

**My mother has an interesting story from her younger days about this.** She was in Los Angeles, in a disco in Hollywood targeted at beautiful white people. She was there with a bunch of her friends, one of which was a really macho italian man. Let’s call him Nico.

On the dance floor, there was one girl who stood out from the rest. She was stunning; with no doubt the most gorgeous of all women there. My mom’s macho italian friend ended up dancing with her.

After quite a while, right after the beauty and the Nico had left the room, a stranger came up to my mom. He had noticed that she was a friend of this macho italian, and said: “someone ought to tell him that she is a he”.

After running out and delivering the message, Nico uttered words so dreadful I probably shouldn’t repeat them here. You could hear him all the way down the road as he rushed into the car and drove away at near the speed of light.

The day after, Nico was still upset. He felt the incident had really injured his masculine ego. He had thought he would be able to differentiate a he from a she.

Most people will probably relate to Nico’s reaction. I know I do at least. Even though what I’d have done and said would have been different, I’d have had basically the same reaction: storm out of there as fast as I could. Who can blame me? Here I am with this beautiful woman, and then bam, someone tells me she’s not a woman at all. Everything I thought I knew about her shatters, and not only isn’t she a woman, she’s not even a man! I mean, where do you place such a person? What properties can you assign to “her”, which box to put “her” in?

That said, what the transgender did was understandable as well. She probably thought about herself as a she. Even before she had various treatments to look like a woman, she thought about herself as a woman. If not she wouldn’t have jumped the gap between the genders would she?

Like most playful young women, she goes to parties and play with boys. There’s nothing questionable here. I mean, what would the alternative be? Not going to parties, not hanging around with friends, not fulfilling your sexual needs, just because you’re neither a woman nor a man? Just because you don’t fulfil society’s expectations of gender as a completely black and white thing, that your gender doesn’t officially exist?

**There’s an interesting report called [“Injustice at Every Turn”](http://endtransdiscrimination.org/PDFs/NTDS_Report.pdf)** by the “National Center For Transgender Equality” and the “National Gay And Lesbian Task Force” in the USA. The report is based on a survey called “the National Transgender Discrimination Survey”.

One of the things this report claims is that 41% of transgender people have attempted suicide. This is insane. The average of the general population is 1.6%. Statistically, the chance for a transgender person to commit suicide is over 25 times as high as someone who’s clearly defined male or female. Transgender people are four times as likely to have an income of less than $10,000 per year. This truly is injustice at every turn.

**It’s clear that we need drastic changes in our society.** First off, we need to stop officially assuming everyone’s either male or female. Men are going to one shower after gym, women are going to another. What about those who are neither? What about those who are both? What if you’ve jumped from one gender to the other, or what if you feel your body isn’t the same gender as your mind? If you’re in any way not clearly female or clearly male, officially you don’t exist. There’s nowhere for you to go. Your gender is inexistent.

Forms are notorious for assuming everyone’s either male or female. There are usually two checkboxes, one labeled “male” and one labeled “female”. There are some forms which do this already, but preferably, all forms should at least include an “other” option in addition to “male” and “female”. I’ve experienced though that people have ridiculed this “other” option when selecting gender, both on the Internet and in person with people sitting close by me filling out the same form as me. This leads me to the second point;

We need to stop unofficially assuming everyone’s either male or female. This is probably the biggest challenge today. As a person in a grey area, where do you go? Who do you play with? Who do you make friends with? Who do you have sex with? All of these questions are really hard to answer. Yet they are the questions you need to answer and you’re going through life if your gender is in a grey area.

The main focus of multiculturalism is to accept cultural differences. Multiculturalism is founded on the idea that cultural differences is important to keep, [according to the Holocaust centre in Norway](http://www.hlsenteret.no/kunnskapsbasen/livssyn/multikulturalisme/multikulturalisme.htm). The more different cultures in a society the richer this society will be.  Therefore, a multicultural society should make an effort to accept people from any gender. Any gender. Not just female or male.
	]]></content>
</entry>
